Guide to the Allan R. Holmberg collection on Peru, circa 1946-1966.
Holmberg, Allan R., collection on Peru, circa 1946-1966
- Series I. Cornell Peru Project (Accession 1)
  - Reprints, Publications and Papers
    - Cornell Comparative Studies of Cultural Change Scientific Reports
      - IV.48. Dobyns, Henry F.; Holmberg, Allan R.; Opler, Morris E.; and Sharp, Lauriston. Methods for Analyzing Cultural Change. Ithaca's Cornell University Department of Anthropology. 1967. (Box 10, Folder 43)
      - IV.49. Dobyns, Henry F.; Holmberg, Allan R.; Opler, Morris E.; and Sharp, Lauriston. Recommendations for Future Research on the Processes of Cultural Change. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology. 1966. (Box 10, Folder 44)
      - IV.50. Dobyns, Henry F.; Holmberg, Allan R.; Opler, Morris E.; and Sharp, Lauriston. Some Principles of Cultural Change. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology. 1967. (Box 10, Folder 45)
      - IV.51. Dobyns, Henry F.; Holmberg, Allan R.; Opler, Morris E.; and Sharp, Lauriston. Strategic Intervention in the Cultural Change Process. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology. 1967. (Box 10, Folder 46)
      - IV.52. Ezell, Paul H. A Comparison of Drinking Patterns in Three Hispanic Cities. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). 1965. (Box 10, Folder 47)
      - IV.53. Flores, Elias J. Modelos de migracion a la Frontera Selvatica. (mimeograph). (Box 10, Folder 48)
      - IV.54. Freeman, David L. La Junta de Obras Publicas de Ancash, A Case Study of a Peruvian Government Agency at Departmental Level. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). 1964. (Box 10, Folder 49)
      - IV.55. Hanks, L.M.; and Hanks, Jane R. "Crisis in Bang Chan," Saturday Review, June, 2, pp. 41-44. 1956. (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - IV.56. Hanks, Lucien M.; Hanks, Jane R.; Sharp, Lauriston; and Sharp, Ruth B. A Report on Tribal Peoples in Chiengrai Province North of the Mae Kok River. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). 1964. (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - IV. 57. The Transformation of the Political, Legal, and Social Systems of Suppressed Peasant Societies: The Vicos Case. Symposium, American Association for the Advancement of Sciences, Montreal, Canada. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology. 26 December 1964., Contains: "The Changing Values and Institutions of Vicos in the Context of National Development" by Allan R. Holmberg; "The Interplay between Power and Wealth" by Mario C. Vazquez; "The Interrelationship of Power, Respect, Affections, and Rectitude in Vicos" by Paul L. Doughty; "The Quest for Well-being" by J. Oscar Alers; "The Strategic Importance of Enlightenment and Skill for Power" by Henry F. Dobyns. (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - IV.58. Holmberg, Allan R.; and Dobyns, Henry F. Case Studies of Subsistence and Transition. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology. 1965. (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - IV.59. Lancaster, Nadja Bee. Hospital De Belen in Huaraz, Peru. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). 1965. (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - IV.60. Mencher, Joan P. Kerala and Madras: A Comparative Study of Ecology and Social Structure. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). 1964-65. (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - IV.61. Morris, Earl W. Culture, Migration, and Fertility in Peru. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - IV.62. Morris, Earl W. Marriage and the Family in Latin America. Ithaca: Cornell University (mimeograph). 1964. (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - IV.63. Murphy. Jane M. Sociocultural Change and Mental Illness Among Yorubas. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). 1965. (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - IV.64. Oberg, Kalervo. Community Development Programs in Puerto Rico. (mimeograph). 1955. (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - IV.65. Oberg, Kalervo. The Government Land Settlement Program in Surinam. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). 1965., 1 volume (Box 11, Folder 11)
      - IV.66. Oberg, Kalervo. A Study of Farm Productivity in the Santo Boma Settlement Project, Surinam. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). 1964. (Box 11, Folder 12)
      - IV.67. Oberg, Kalervo. Water Supply Development Through Joint Action. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). 1964. (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - IV.68. Opler, Morris E. a. "Particularization and Generalization as Processes in Ritual and Culture," The Journal of Asian Studies, XXIII (June, 1964), 83-87. b. "Cultural Context and Population Control Programs in Village India," Fact and Theory in Social Science, ed. by Earl W. Count and Gordon T. Bowles. Syracuse: Syracuse University Press, pp. 201-221. 1964. c. "Morgan and Materialism: A Reply to Professor Opler," and "Reply," Current Anthropology, 5:2, pp. 109-114. (1964). d. "Values and Education in Cultural Perspective," Values in American Education, ed. by Theodore Brameld and Stanley Elam. Bloomington: Phi Delta Kappa, pp. 115-137. 1964. (Box 11, Folder 14)
      - IV.69. Opler, Morris E.; et al. The South Asian Village--A bibliography. (mimeograph). 1964. (Box 11, Folder 15)
      - IV.70. Portugal, Jose; and Cheng, Alberto. Migration en el Valle de Lurin. Lima: Instituto de Etnologia y Archeologia. Universidad de San Marcos (mimeograph). 1961. (Box 11, Folder 16)
      - IV.71. Richards, Cara E. Dine Bitoh: Navajo Water Use. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). 1964. (Box 11, Folder 17)
      - IV.72. Richards, Cara E. Some Changes in Navajo Diet. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). 1964. (Box 11, Folder 18)
      - IV.73. Sabogal W., Jose R. Sumario sobre la economia de migracion. (mimeograph). (Box 11, Folder 19)
      - IV.74. Smith, Robert J. Town and City in "Pre-Modern" Japan: Small Families, Small Households, and Residential Instability. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). 1964. (Box 11, Folder 20)
      - IV.75. Soler, Eduardo. Fuentes de migracion al complejo agricola-industrial de Paramonga. (mimeograph). (Box 11, Folder 21)
      - IV.76. Solis, Cesar A. Fuentes de migracion al puerto industrial de Chimbote. (mimeograph). 1961. (Box 11, Folder 22)
      - IV.77. Thanhauser, Ralph J. A Peruvian Trucking Industry. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). 1965. (Box 11, Folder 23)
      - IV.78. Vazquez, Mario C. Aquia and Caranavi: Two Cases of Internal Migration in the Andes. Ithaca: Cornell University (mimeograph). (Box 11, Folder 24)
      - IV.79. Vazquez, Mario C. The "Castas": Unilinear Kin Groups in Vicos, Peru. Ithaca: Cornell University (mimeograph). 1964. (Box 11, Folder 25)
      - IV.80. Vazquez, Mario C. Chicha in the Central Andean Countries. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). (Box 11, Folder 26)
      - IV.81. Vazquez, Mario C. Two Cases of Internal Migration in the Andes. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). 1966. (Box 11, Folder 27)
      - IV.82. Vazquez, Mario C. The Varayoc System in Vicos. Ithaca: Cornell University (mimeograph). 1964. (Box 11, Folder 28)
      - IV.83. Vazquez, Mario C. Viru: Land and Society. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). (Box 11, Folder 29)
      - IV.84. Vazquez, Mario C.; and Dobyns, Henry F. The Transformation of Manors into Producers' Cooperatives. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). 1964. (Box 11, Folder 30)
      - IV.85. Vazquez, Mario C.; and Holmberg, Allan R. The Castas: Unilinear Kin Groups in Vicos, Peru. Ithaca: Cornell University (mimeograph). 1965. (Box 11, Folder 31)
    - Andean Indian Community Research and Development Program Scientific Reports
      - V.86. Bradfield, Stillman. "Some Occupational Aspects of Migration," Economic Development and Cultural Change, XIV:l (Oct.) pp. 61-70. 1965. (Box 11, Folder 32)
      - V.87. Dobyns, Henry F. Farm-Market Roads in Nation Development in the Central Andes. (mimeograph). (Box 11, Folder 33)
      - IV.88. Maynard, Eileen A. Indians in Misery. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology. 1965. (Box 11, Folder 34)
      - V.89. Maynard, Eileen; Frølund, Bjarke; and Rasmussen, Christian. Drinking Patterns in Highland Ecuador. Ithaca: Cornell University Department of Anthropology (mimeograph). 1965. (Box 11, Folder 35)
      - Vazquez, Mario C. Report on the Kami Mine. 2 volumes., 1966 (Box 11, Folder 36-37)
  - Microfilms, Audiotapes and Motion Picture Film
    Most of the tapes and microfilms were obtained by CPP personnel while working on publications. Some of the information is marginally related to the rest of the collection.
    On one audio tape Rose K. Goldsen, Director of the Cornell Methodology Project in Vicos, discusses the material accessioned by the Cornell Archives as the Vicos Collection. There is a transcript of an interview with William Stein, a former CPP researcher, discussing the same subject. The rest of the tapes are from a conference on Puerto Rican studies, held at Cornell in the early sixties.
    There are microfilms of dissertations, records of Bolivian mining operations, and some unidentified material from Puerto Rico. The microfilms of the Bolivian mine records were used in ethnohistorical background research by CPP personnel. The dissertation microfilms are of studies done in Latin America. They were written between 1949 and 1972 (the 1972 dissertation was added by Deborah Wood) and include a wide variety of topics.
    The motion picture films were added to the collection in 2004 and contain footage of the Vicosinos and Peru in general. All of the films have been digitized and researchers should use the digital copies not the original films. There is also a copy of the 1962 CBS film So That Men Are Free. This film was not digitized by Cornell because of copyright considerations, but it is available on-line from the University of Cambridge at http://www.dspace.cam.ac.uk/handle/1810/56
    - Rose K. Goldsen discussing material accessioned as the Vicos Collection, Audiotape (Box 19)
    - William W. Stein discussing material accessioned as the Vicos Collection, Transcript (Box 19)
    - Harwood, Ruth, "An Experiment in Community Development in El Salvador", 1963; Microfilm (Box 33)
    - Hagen, Edmund Edward, "Highways Into the Amazon", 1962; Microfilm (Box 33)
    - Himes, James R., "The Utilization of Research for Development: Two Case Studies in Rural Modernization and Agriculture in Peru", 1972; Microfilm (Box 33)
    - Hundley, Norris C. Jr., "Dividing the Waters: Mexican-American Controversies Over the Waters of The Colorado River and the Rio Grande", 1880-1960; Microfilm (Box 33)
    - Keller, Frank L., "Geography of the Lake Titicaca Basin of Bolivia", 1949; Microfilm (Box 33)
    - Klein, Ralph, "The Self-Image of Adult Males in an Andean Culture", 1963; Microfilm (Box 33)
    - Puerto Rico--Various (3 films) also 8 tapes of conference--Puerto Rico. (Box 33)
    - "Aramayo" Bolivia: Records of mining contracts and companies, 1944-1951; (11 positive and 11 negative microfilms) (Box 33)
    - Meetings, music, dance, procession, 1960; 5-3" reel audiotapes (Box 33)
    - Lima, undated; 1-3" reel audiotape (Box 33)
    - Church music, undated; 1-3" reel audiotape (Box 33)
    - Eric & a.d., undated; 1-3" reel audiotape (Box 33)
    - Music, school children, meetings, 1954-1955; 4-5" reel audiotapes (Box 33)
    - Unidentified, undated; 2-5" reel audiotapes (Box 33)
    - Prof. Allan Holmberg, "The Vicos Project and Community Development in Latin America, April 7, 1965", 1-7" reel audiotape (Box 33)
    - Unidentified, undated; 3-7" reel audiotapes (Box 33)
    - Peru-Vicos, 1954 Funeral Demonstrations in Huaraz after Huapra Massacre General views of Peru [General shots of Callejon de Huaylas, agriculture (plowing, spraying, harvesting etc.), funeral, Vicos celebrations and rituals, village militia training, children playing and at school, building and inaugurating school, nationalist symbols (flag in community, more militia training), hair cuts at school and shots of school], DVD 1 (Box 33)
      The original films are in box 32 but they are not available for research use.
    - Potatoes, 1952 Miscellaneous Vicos footage, DVD 2 (Box 33)
    - Various Vicos and Peru footage, 6-16mm motion picture films (Box 32)
      Originals - not for public use - please use digitized versions in box 33
    - So That Men Are Free, 1962; 1-16mm motion picture film; Filmed by CBS. Narrated by Walter Cronkite. (Box 32)
      Available on-line at http://www.dspace.cam.ac.uk/handle/1810/56 [link opens new window; site not affiliated with Cornell University]
  - Visual Materials
    The material in this subseries adds to the depth of the collection by providing a visual dimension to documentation. Photographs and slides are clear and present a wide variety of scenes. The slides include scenes from Vicos, the Callejon de Huaylas, Cuzco and Bolivia.
    Some photographs of Vicos, showing the setting and impact of the CPP, were mounted as an exhibition collection. John Collier, Jr. and Abraham Guillen did a good deal of photography for the project; it is quite possible that they took these photographs although there are no labels. There are also mounted photographs depicting other places in Peru.
    May Kedney, although not connected with the CPP, taught in the Vicos school the summer of 1954. The paintings by Vicosino boys were produced under her supervision. As an art instructor at Skidmore College, Saratoga Springs, NY, she was interested in how artwork by Vicosino children would compare in subject and style with that of American children. Vicosino children had not done artwork of this type before. They started painting with clay pigments on newspaper, using brushes made from horse tail hair set in builder's glue. Later Kedney got water colors and plain paper. She also gave the boys some clay to model.
    - Photographs
      - Callejon de Huaylas (1) (Mapcase-folder 5)
      - Recuayhuanca, Ancash (1) (Box 57)
      - Mayobamba, Ancash (2) (Mapcase-folder 12)
      - Viru, Ancash (1) (Mapcase-folder 5)
      - Sacsahuaman (Box 58)
      - Machu Picchu (Box 58)
      - Unidentified Portrait (Box 58)
      - Colquiri, Bolivia by Carlos Hochmann, 1965; 49 panoramic, white-mounted (Mapcase-folder 12-14)
      - Colquiri, Bolivia by Carlos Hochmann, 1965; 9 green-mounted, small photos (Box 57)
      - Colquiri, Bolivia by Carlos Hochmann, 1965; 18 panoramic, white-mounted (Box 58)
      - Negative--Women Harvesting in Vicos (Box 30)
      - 2 black-and-white photographs of Vicosinos, Abraham Guillen (Box 30)
      - Artifacts (Box 31, Folder 4)
      - Bolivia (Box 31, Folder 5)
      - Cuzco (Box 31, Folder 6)
      - Forte Principe de Beira (Box 31, Folder 7)
      - Huara (Box 31, Folder 8)
      - Lima (Box 31, Folder 9)
      - Puno (Box 31, Folder 10)
      - Sand Dunes - Coast of Peru (Box 31, Folder 11)
      - Tomabal (Box 31, Folder 12)
      - #1-62 (not complete series) (Box 31, Folder 13)
      - Unidentified costumes/dress (Box 31, Folder 14)
      - Unidentified festival: dancers (Box 31, Folder 15)
      - Unidentified festival: musicians (Box 31, Folder 16)
      - Vicos (unidentified) (Box 31, Folder 17)
      - Unidentified (Box 31, Folder 18-23)
      - Miscellaneous negatives, Vicos (Box 31, Folder 24)
      - Callejon de Huaylas and Cordillera Blanca (2) and Viru, 3 aerial photographs (Mapcase-folder 5)
      - Aerial photo of land plots in Vicos - Plano 5, circa 1952-1962; RMC2004_5365; Silver gelatin print (Box 14)
        Panoramic view originally (1952-1962) taken with four photographs, which were then cut to piece together the entire scene. The four photograph pieces were scanned together to show the entire image of the land plots [June 2004].
        In folder titled "Estudios de los terrenos de Vicos"
      - Three men spraying DDT on crops, 1955; RMC2004_5200; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Agriculture activities: Cornell-Peru Project, spraying DDT
      - Using short handled hoe, farming corn field, circa 1955-1965; RMC2004_5201; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Male peasant and boy farming a corn field with short handled hoe. Traditional peasant house in the background. "Corn being cultivated by short handled hoe. Child in the picture would or could be anywhere from eight to fourteen years old."
      - Shepherd woman: raising sheep in pastures, 1955; RMC2004_5202; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Female peasant and children herding sheep in natural grasslands or pastures.
      - School children learning to read and write, 1955; RMC2004_5203; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Educational activities: Cornell-Peru Project, 3 school boys looking at a reading-writing workbook.
      - School children at the hot lunch program, 1955; RMC2004_5204; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Educational activities: Cornell-Peru Project, children at the hot lunch program. several boy and girl students sitting and eating at a large table at the new school building. Two adults are in the picture.
        See also Digital ID Number: RMC2004_5221.
      - Learning at the new school, 1955; RMC2004_5205; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Educational activities: Cornell-Peru Project, children and teacher at the new school.
        See also Digital ID Number: RMC2004_5225.
      - Building with adobe bricks, 1955; RMC2004_5206; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Communal activities: Cornell-Peru Project, peasants building a house using adobe bricks.
      - Allan Holmberg and a peasant in a crop land plot, 1955; RMC2004_5207; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Cornell-Peru Project Director, Allan Holmberg, and a young peasant.
      - Women Desgranando (shelling) corn, 1955; RMC2004_5208; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Image of three women (more are out of frame) sitting down shelling corn in a room with the floors filled with shucked corn.
      - Four Vicosian men making adobe bricks, 1955; RMC2004_5209; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Four men making rows of adobe bricks in a field using brick moulds.
      - Reading poetry at the new school, circa 1955-1962; RMC2004_5210; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Inside the new school building. Children are sitting at their desks, several are looking backwards at the camera. One student is at the chalk board using a pointer and reading a poem. A teacher is standing in front of the class.
      - Shepherd Girl and her dog, circa 1955-1962; RMC2004_5211; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        "A girl herding sheep and weaving (?) at the same time." The dog was looking directly at the camera.
      - Portrait of Vicosina girl, circa 1955-1962; RMC2004_5212; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Picture of a very young Vicosina girl
      - Landscape with sheep and shepherd's hut, circa 1955-1962; RMC2004_5213; Gelatin silver print (Map-case ?)
      - Weighing potatoes, circa 1955-1962; RMC2004_5214; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Viscosian man weighing potatoes and pouring them into a clean cotton sack held by a boy.
      - Plowing the land with oxen, circa 1955-1962; RMC2004_5215; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Inscription on back of picture: 1. A single stick plow with a sharp steel point no mold board. 2. Introduced by the Spanidars in 15th Century - still in use today (circa 1950).
      - Peasants preparing chemical pesticide (DDT) in the field, circa 1955-1962; RMC2004_5216; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
      - Mario Vazquez and a peasant spraying the crops with DDT, circa 1955-1962; RMC2004_5217; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
      - Vicosian women and girls winnowing corn, circa 1955-1962; RMC2004_5218; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
      - Vicos Farmer clearing an irrigation ditch, circa 1955-1962; RMC2004_5219; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
      - May Kedney and school boys making art in Vicos school, 1954; RMC2004_5220; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        May Kedney in the new school building with eight students making art using paper, scissors, paste and crayons.
      - School children at the hot lunch school program in the renovated building, circa 1954-1955; RMC2004_5221; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Two rows of school children sit and eat at a large table, watched by three adults.
      - Children washing before entering the school, circa 1954-1962; RMC2004_5222; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        A Girl and a Boy wash their faces and hands from a large bowl of water on the ground.
      - Building the new school, circa 1952-1955; RMC2004_5223; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Bricklaying by peasants of additional rooms for the school buildings. Completed new building is visible in the background.
      - School children cutting each others hair, circa 1954-1956; RMC2004_5224; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        One school child with a shaven head is shaving the head of another school child outside the new school.
      - Inside the old Vicos school, 1950s; RMC2004_5225; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Picture of inside of the old school with several students seated at tables and their teacher.
      - Inside the old Vicos school, 1950s; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Picture of inside of the old school with several students seated at table and their teacher.
      - The new school build by the Vicosinos, 1950s; RMC2004_5226; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
      - Pay day at Hacienda Vicos, 1950s; RMC2004_5227; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Inside picture of several Vicos peasants (men and women) waiting to be paid. One man is receiving his money from another who is checking a list and has piles of coins on a table. At least two men are CPP staff.
      - Cornell-Peru Project research team in the village of Vicos., 1950s; RMC2004_5228; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Group picture of twelve people (nine men and three women) posed in front of a truck and building in Vicos.
      - Cornell-Peru Project research team photo taken in the field., 1950s; RMC2004_5229; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Picture of eleven CPP researchers (eight men and three women) sitting atop a hill with mountains in the background. Inscription on back of picture, "Vicos Research Team. Dr. Allan Holmberg is sitting on the ground, 3rd from the right. The woman standing 4th from the left might(?) be Joan Snyder, who did her Ph.D. research in the nearby village of Recuayhuanca. - A. Fairchild, 8-1981."
      - Allan Holmberg, Mario Vazquez and two peasants weighing harvested potatoes., circa 1955-1962; RMC2004_5230; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Vazquez weighing potatoes on a scale while two peasant men and Dr. Holmberg watch. The are in front of a building.
      - Cornell-Peru Project researcher and a Vicos peasant, circa 1955-1962; RMC2004_5231; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        CPP researcher (NOT Dr. Holmberg) taking notes talking with a Vicos peasant who is sitting on a rock next to a haystack.
      - Vicos adobe building, circa 1952-1962; RMC2004_5232; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
        Large conjoined adobe building with work yard in front and mountains behind.
      - Cordillera Blanca high plains, circa 1952-1962; RMC2004_5233; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
      - View of Vicos agricultural land plots, circa 1952-1962; RMC2004_5234; Gelatin silver print (Box 56)
      - Vicos landscape with pasture and buildings, circa 1952-1962; RMC2004_5235; Gelatin silver print (Box 57)
      - Aerial photo of Quebrada Honda, August 30, 1948; RMC2004_5236; Gelatin silver print (Mapcase-folder 14)